<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>The Reuther Lab</title>
<link>https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/</link>
<atom:link href="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<image>
<url>https://reutherlab.netlify.app/logosimple.webp</url>
<title>The Reuther Lab</title>
<link>https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/</link>
</image>
<generator>quarto-1.5.57</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>A Brief Guide to Data Privacy and GenAI Chatbots</title>
  <dc:creator>Keefe Reuther</dc:creator>
  <link>https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/aiprivacypolicy/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<hr>
<section id="key-points-to-consider" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-points-to-consider">Key Points to Consider</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Data Usage for Model Training</strong>
<ul>
<li><strong>OpenAI’s ChatGPT</strong>:
<ul>
<li>By default, any content you input—including prompts, file uploads, and feedback—may be used to improve their services, including training AI models like ChatGPT. They don’t use content from business offerings such as ChatGPT Team, ChatGPT Enterprise, and their API Platform to train models.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Anthropic’s Claude</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Anthropic will <strong>not</strong> use your inputs or outputs to train their models <strong>unless</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Your conversations are flagged for Trust &amp; Safety review.</li>
<li>You explicitly report materials via feedback mechanisms.</li>
<li>You have explicitly opted in to the use of your inputs and outputs for training purposes.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Data Retention Policies</strong>
<ul>
<li><strong>OpenAI</strong> retains records of your interactions for up to <strong>30 days</strong>, even if you opt out, to monitor for misuse or abuse before deleting them.</li>
<li><strong>Anthropic</strong> allows you to delete individual conversations, which will be removed immediately from your conversation history and automatically deleted from their back-end systems within <strong>30 days</strong>.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Legal Disclosures and Third-Party Access</strong>
<ul>
<li>Both OpenAI and Anthropic may disclose your content to comply with legal obligations, meaning your data could potentially be accessed by third parties under certain circumstances.</li>
<li>Data may also be shared with affiliates and service providers who process data on their behalf.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Best Practices for Protecting IP and Student Privacy</strong>
<ul>
<li><strong>De-identify Sensitive Information</strong>: Always remove or anonymize any personal, student-related, or proprietary information before inputting it into AI tools.</li>
<li><strong>Avoid Sharing Protected Data</strong>: Do not input any data that could violate FERPA regulations or disclose confidential research.</li>
<li><strong>Stay Informed</strong>: Regularly review the privacy policies of these AI services to stay updated on how your data is handled.</li>
<li><strong>Institutional Guidelines</strong>: Ensure compliance with your institution’s policies regarding the use of AI tools and data privacy.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="actionable-steps" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="actionable-steps">Actionable Steps</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Opt Out of Data Usage for Training</strong>:
<ul>
<li><p>For <strong>ChatGPT</strong>, follow the opt-out instructions below.</p>
<ul>
<li><p><img src="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/aiprivacypolicy/privacy1.png" class="img-fluid"></p></li>
<li><p><img src="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/aiprivacypolicy/privacy2.png" class="img-fluid"></p></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>For <strong>Claude</strong>, refrain from opting in to data usage for training and avoid submitting feedback that could be used for this purpose.</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Delete Unnecessary Conversations</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Regularly delete any conversations that may contain sensitive information to minimize data retention risks.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Exercise Caution with Input Content</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Be mindful of the information you share in AI chat windows. When in doubt, rephrase or generalize the content to avoid including identifiable information.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Consider Going Local</strong>:
<ul>
<li>While it takes a bit of technical training, you can run many high quality LLM models locally. If interested, <a href="https://huggingface.co">Hugging Face</a> is the place to go for Open Source models. Also check out <a href="https://ollama.com/">Ollama</a> for a more user friendly interface.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="additional-resources" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="additional-resources">Additional Resources</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://openai.com/policies/row-privacy-policy/">ChatGPT Privacy Policy</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.anthropic.com/legal/privacy">Anthropic Privacy Policy</a></li>
</ul>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{reuther2024,
  author = {Reuther, Keefe},
  title = {A {Brief} {Guide} to {Data} {Privacy} and {GenAI} {Chatbots}},
  date = {2024-10-16},
  url = {https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/aiprivacypolicy/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-reuther2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Reuther, Keefe. 2024. <span>“A Brief Guide to Data Privacy and GenAI
Chatbots.”</span> October 16, 2024. <a href="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/aiprivacypolicy/">https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/aiprivacypolicy/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>AI</category>
  <category>Undergraduate</category>
  <category>Instructor</category>
  <guid>https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/aiprivacypolicy/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/aiprivacypolicy/security.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>SABER Generative AI Special Interest Group</title>
  <dc:creator>Keefe Reuther</dc:creator>
  <link>https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/genaisig/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The Special Interest Group on Generative AI in Biology Education Research (BER) aims to leverage the collective expertise of SABER members to integrate GenAI tools like ChatGPT into biology education, fostering innovation and addressing pedagogical needs. Reach out to Keefe Reuther to get involved!</p>
<hr>
<section id="objective" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="objective">Objective</h2>
<p>The rapid advancement and integration of Generative Artificial Intelligence (GenAI) into educational environments present both opportunities and challenges. This Special Interest Group aims to forefront the exploration of GenAI tools, such as ChatGPT, in the biology classroom. By fostering a collaborative network, this SIG seeks to harness the collective expertise of SABER members to pioneer innovative educational methodologies, enhance student learning experiences, and address the evolving needs of educators in the realm of biology education research.</p>
</section>
<section id="potential-key-activities-and-goals" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="potential-key-activities-and-goals">Potential Key Activities and Goals</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Facilitate Networking and Collaboration:</strong> Create a vibrant community of educators, researchers, and technologists dedicated to integrating GenAI into biology education. This network will serve as a platform for sharing insights, best practices, and fostering partnerships that could lead to impactful collaborative research and training.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Conduct a Comprehensive Survey:</strong> Launch a detailed survey targeting SABER members to capture a broad spectrum of views, experiences, and pedagogical needs related to the use of GenAI in teaching biology. The insights gained will inform the development of resources, specialized talks, and training workshops tailored to the community’s needs.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Develop a Strategic Framework for BER and GenAI:</strong> Articulate a forward-looking framework that outlines key research priorities, potential challenges, and opportunities presented by GenAI in biology education. This framework will guide future scholarly inquiries and the integration of AI technologies in pedagogical practices.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Curating a Repository of Generative AI Tools, Resources, and Learning Activities:</strong> Assemble and maintain a comprehensive collection of GenAI tools, educational resources, and innovative learning activities specifically designed for biology education.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="why-join-us" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-join-us">Why Join Us?</h2>
<p>Engaging with the SIG on GenAI in BER offers a unique opportunity to be at the forefront of educational innovation. Members will gain early insights into the transformative potential of GenAI, influence the development of teaching resources and research agendas, and contribute to a pioneering effort to shape the future of biology education.</p>
</section>
<section id="get-involved" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="get-involved">Get Involved</h2>
<p>We invite all SABER members interested in exploring the intersection of GenAI and biology education to join this exciting initiative. Whether you’re a seasoned educator, a curious researcher, or an innovator at heart, your contributions are valuable in steering the fruitful integration of GenAI into biology education research. No technical experience required - just the curiosity and drive to learn about these rapidly emerging and evolving tools.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{reuther2024,
  author = {Reuther, Keefe},
  title = {SABER {Generative} {AI} {Special} {Interest} {Group}},
  date = {2024-02-16},
  url = {https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/genaisig/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-reuther2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Reuther, Keefe. 2024. <span>“SABER Generative AI Special Interest
Group.”</span> February 16, 2024. <a href="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/genaisig/">https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/genaisig/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>AI</category>
  <category>Instructors</category>
  <guid>https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/genaisig/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 16 Feb 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/genaisig/saber.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="64" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Science of Asking: How to Formulate Questions and Hypotheses in Research</title>
  <dc:creator>Keefe Reuther</dc:creator>
  <link>https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/statistical_thinking/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Asking questions and testing them scientifically is a skill that requires both simplicity in approach and intentional practice. Despite often feeling intuitive, it’s a challenging skill to master. Here, we explore a structured approach to formulate questions and test hypotheses while minimizing bias.</p>
<p><img src="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/statistical_thinking/stat_thoughts.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<section id="a-short-primer-connecting-scientific-questions-to-statistical-conclusions" class="level1">
<h1>A Short Primer Connecting Scientific Questions to Statistical Conclusions</h1>
<p>Asking questions and testing them scientifically is a skill that requires both simplicity in approach and intentional practice. Despite often feeling intuitive, it’s a challenging skill to master. Here, we explore a structured approach to formulate questions and test hypotheses while minimizing bias.</p>
<section id="part-1-formulating-your-question" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="part-1-formulating-your-question">Part 1: Formulating Your Question</h2>
<p>The key to asking a scientific question is specificity. Consider the ‘Who, What, Where, When, How, and Why’ of your question. Evaluating the context and underlying assumptions is crucial in minimizing bias.</p>
<p><strong>Example of a Vague Scientific Question:</strong> How effective is the Pfizer vaccine?</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Who?</strong> Are we talking about a specific age group, sex, health history? Be specific about the group you want to learn about.</li>
<li><strong>What?</strong> Clarify what “effective” means in this context. Are we talking about preventing any infection, any symptoms, or preventing hospitalization or death?</li>
<li><strong>Where?</strong> Choose the location for your study carefully. A study in one country may not be easily generalizable to another.</li>
<li><strong>When?</strong> When will the data be collected and how often will individuals be tested? Are we collecting short or long-term health data? Might data be collected at a time when a particularly nasty COVID variant is prevalent?</li>
<li><strong>How?</strong> How will you collect data? Will you use questionnaires or will you test subjects for COVID? Each method has its own errors and biases</li>
<li><strong>Why?</strong> What is your reason for conducting your experiment? Are people’s lives at stake? The answer to this may affect the amount of error you allow when making conclusions or recommendations.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="part-2-the-importance-of-sampling" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="part-2-the-importance-of-sampling">Part 2: The importance of sampling</h2>
<p>The scope of your question will likely be broader than the sample you are actually able to test in your experiment.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Example: Let’s say your question asks about the efficacy of the Pfizer vaccine in preventing COVID-related hospitalization in all adults over 16 years old. Will you be able to test ALL adults over the age of 16? No, you might be able to test as many as 50,000, but that is just a subset of the group you are asking about.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Your question addresses a broader group, but your experiment will only measure a sample of it. This means there are two potential answers:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>The effect that exists in reality for the entire group of interest.</p></li>
<li><p>The effect observed in your data collected from your sample.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>You aim for these answers to be the same, but discrepancies can occur, and that’s not necessarily your fault.</p>
</section>
<section id="part-3-how-uncertain-are-we-in-our-results" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="part-3-how-uncertain-are-we-in-our-results">Part 3: How uncertain are we in our results?</h2>
<p>After running your experiment and collecting data, it’s important to evaluate the likelihood of inaccuracies.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/statistical_thinking/table.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Table of Possibilities in Hypothesis Testing</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As a researcher, you are hoping your results match reality (true positive or negative). Through good design and analysis, you hope to minimize and measure the probability your results are different from reality (false positive or negative).</p>
<section id="understanding-false-positives-and-magical-mysterious-p-value" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="understanding-false-positives-and-magical-mysterious-p-value">Understanding False Positives and magical, mysterious P-value:</h4>
<p>Take your two types of hypotheses:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Alternate hypotheses: There is an effect! Vaccine is more effective than placebo.</p></li>
<li><p>Null hypothesis: There is NO effect. Vaccines are equal in efficacy with placebo.</p></li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Assuming the null hypothesis is true, the p-value is the probability that you could have gotten your results or something more extremely different by chance.</strong> The lower this probability is, the more likely your results represent a true positive (i.e.&nbsp;significantly different experimental groups).</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For example, let’s say you have a perfectly fair coin (i.e.&nbsp;the null hypothesis is true and the probability of flipping heads or tails is the same). You flip the coin 10 times and get 2 heads. Doesn’t sound like a fair coin, but what is the probability of flipping 2 heads by chance with a fair coin? About 4.4%. The p value would be the probability of flipping two heads or something more extreme. This would be the sum of the probabilities of flipping 0, 1, 2, 8, 9, and 10 heads, which happens to be ~11% or a p value = 0.11.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>Yet another way to think about p-values:</strong> Let’s say you run your experiment and have a p-value of 0.05. YAY! It’s a significant difference and I won science and all my grants will get funded! Well…maybe. Once again, let’s assume the null is actually true. And imagine you ran your exact same experiment 100 different times. In 5 of those experiments, by random chance, you would think there is a difference but there really isn’t. How do you know whether your results are part of that rare 5% and your positive results are a random fluke? You don’t. Only replication and higher sample size might help you better figure that out.</p>
<p><strong>So why is 0.05 the magical p-value number of significance?</strong> No particularly specific reason. Historically it was recommended by R. Fisher in 1925 out of convenience. Everything had to be calculated by hand at that time anyway.</p>
<p>This threshold is called the alpha value and the researcher should set it based on the amount of risk they are willing to assume if the results are a false positive. That is why the significance threshold should be as low as 0.01 or 0.0001 if you’re testing the safety of a medicine that could possibly result in death.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-about-false-negatives-arent-they-powerfully-important-too" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-about-false-negatives-arent-they-powerfully-important-too">What about false negatives? Aren’t they powerfully important too?</h4>
<p>P-values don’t directly tell us anything about the power of an analysis, which is the ability of our experiment to see an effect that is actually present.</p>
<div class="line-block"><strong>Statistical power = 1 - the probability of a false negative.</strong></div>
<p>Good power is often thought to be around .80. This means that if an effect is present, your data analysis will see it 80% of the time. Unfortunately, much of the research published today has much lower power AND it’s often not reported in articles. Isn’t this awful? Tell me about it! Change the system and speak truth to power.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="part-4---how-do-i-put-all-of-this-together" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="part-4---how-do-i-put-all-of-this-together">Part 4 - How do I put all of this together?</h2>
<p><strong>Does a p-value tell us anything about effect size (i.e.&nbsp;how different two groups are)?</strong> No, not directly. This is often measured by a statistic called Cohen’s D or Glass’ Delta. It’s also not reported as often as it should be.</p>
<p><strong>Well that doesn’t sound right. What should I do?</strong> It’s good to report all relevant statistics: p-value, power, sample size, and effect size. In fact, these are things you should incorporate as early as the design phase of your experiment:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Determine the effect size you’d like to be able to see in your experiment. Sometimes you don’t need to be able to tell if the difference between groups is 0.001%.</p></li>
<li><p>Determine the power and p-value thresholds you are comfortable with BEFORE you collect all your data.</p></li>
<li><p>Decide on the appropriate statistical test(s) you’ll use to test your hypothesis.</p></li>
<li><p>Use a power analysis to estimate the sample size needed to be able to see a given effect at your proposed power.</p></li>
<li><p>Run your experiment with that sample size and calculate the actual (i.e.&nbsp;post-hoc) measures of power, effect size, and p-value. Report your results.</p></li>
<li><p>Don’t selectively change your analysis, experimental design, or reduce/increase sample size without sufficient reason. Doing so is p-hacking and N-hacking and leads to biased results and conclusions.&nbsp;</p></li>
</ul>
<p><em>At UCSD, courses like BILD 5 and Math 11, as well as degree programs in Biostatistics, delve deeper into these topics.</em></p>


</section>
</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{reuther2024,
  author = {Reuther, Keefe},
  title = {The {Science} of {Asking:} {How} to {Formulate} {Questions}
    and {Hypotheses} in {Research}},
  date = {2024-01-17},
  url = {https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/statistical_thinking/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-reuther2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Reuther, Keefe. 2024. <span>“The Science of Asking: How to Formulate
Questions and Hypotheses in Research.”</span> January 17, 2024. <a href="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/statistical_thinking/">https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/statistical_thinking/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Experimental Design</category>
  <category>Statistics</category>
  <category>Undergraduates</category>
  <guid>https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/statistical_thinking/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Crafting Your GenAI &amp; AI Policy Guide</title>
  <dc:creator>Keefe Reuther and Tricia Bertram-Gallant</dc:creator>
  <link>https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/craftingaipolicy/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Find my personal GenAI syllabus policy and a comprehensive guide authored by Dr.&nbsp;Tricia Bertram-Gallant, director of the Academic Integrity Office and the Triton Testing Center at UC San Diego.</p>
<hr>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/craftingaipolicy/ai_cheating.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>https://academicintegrity.ucsd.edu/excel-integrity/ai-in-education.html</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="my-personal-genai-policy-template" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="my-personal-genai-policy-template">My personal GenAI policy template</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<h3 id="academic-integrity-policy-on-the-use-of-generative-ai" class="anchored">Academic Integrity Policy on the Use of Generative AI</h3>
<p><strong><em>TLDR: Generative AI is transformative for the workplace and beyond. I encourage you to embrace it, but use it wisely and ethically.</em></strong></p>
<h4 id="philosophical-overview" class="anchored">Philosophical Overview</h4>
<p>Generative AI is neutral by nature, neither good nor bad. Its value hinges on how it’s applied. We acknowledge AI’s potential to both elevate and diminish the academic experience. While it’s a powerful tool for the digital age and essential for our future, it doesn’t absolve us from upholding academic integrity and opposing plagiarism.</p>
<h4 id="personal-responsibility-and-accountability" class="anchored">Personal Responsibility and Accountability</h4>
<p>You own your work. AI can assist, but it shouldn’t be the main contributor. If your work appears overly dependent on AI, expect an oral quiz to test your understanding. Remember: mastering AI, like any skill, takes effort. Over-relying on it shortchanges your education and has lasting consequences.<br>
</p>
<h4 id="attribution-and-documentation" class="anchored">Attribution and Documentation</h4>
<p>Using AI-generated content? Document:</p>
<ul>
<li>Prompts given to the AI: “&lt;List prompt(s)&gt;”</li>
<li>AI’s direct output: “<paste the="" output="" generated="" by="" ai="" system="">”</paste></li>
<li>Your modifications to the output: “<explain the="" actions="" taken="">”</explain></li>
<li>How did you verify the information? Did you run the code or did you have to fact-check online?</li>
</ul>
<p>Include this documentation in your references/citations. It won’t impact word or page limits.</p>
<p><strong>Example:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Prompt for ChatGPT: “Discuss the impact of climate change on marine biodiversity.”</li>
<li>AI’s output: “Climate change has led to ocean acidification, causing coral bleaching and marine species decline.”</li>
<li>My modifications: Added recent stats and specific species examples and I fact-checked the gen AI claims at: <a href="https://oceanservice.noaa.gov/facts/coralreef-climate.html">How does climate change affect coral reefs?</a><br>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="disclaimer-on-generative-ai" class="anchored">Disclaimer on Generative AI</h4>
<p>Generative AI, such as ChatGPT, can sometimes produce misleading or false information. You’re accountable for every submission, AI-assisted or not. ALWAYS fact-check AI-generated content before submission.</p>
<p><br>
</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="the-genai-policy-guide-created-by-dr.-tricia-bertram-gallant" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-genai-policy-guide-created-by-dr.-tricia-bertram-gallant">The GenAI policy guide created by Dr.&nbsp;Tricia Bertram-Gallant</h2>
<p><br>
I <strong>HIGHLY</strong> recommend this guide for all instructors, regardless of what your policy will be.<br>
<a href="https://academicintegrity.ucsd.edu/">UCSD Academic Integrity Office</a></p>
<embed src="Crafting Your  GenAI &amp; AI Policy  Guide.pdf" type="application/pdf" iframe="" width="100%" height="800">


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{reuther_and_tricia_bertram-gallant2024,
  author = {Reuther and Tricia Bertram-Gallant, Keefe},
  title = {Crafting {Your} {GenAI} \&amp; {AI} {Policy} {Guide}},
  date = {2024-01-13},
  url = {https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/craftingaipolicy/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-reuther_and_tricia_bertram-gallant2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Reuther and Tricia Bertram-Gallant, Keefe. 2024. <span>“Crafting Your
GenAI &amp; AI Policy Guide.”</span> January 13, 2024. <a href="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/craftingaipolicy/">https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/craftingaipolicy/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/craftingaipolicy/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jan 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/craftingaipolicy/ucsdintegrity.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="79" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Gathering Perspectives on Generative AI in Undergraduate Biology Education</title>
  <link>https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/saberwestsurvey/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><a href="https://sites.google.com/uci.edu/saber-west-2024/home">SABER West Conference 2024</a></p>
<hr>
<p>Since the public release of ChatGPT in November 2022, generative AI has rapidly entered the college classroom. New capabilities are continually emerging that impact teaching and learning environments. In higher education broadly, there has been an influx of conferences, preprints, publications, and working groups examining implications and applications of generative AI. However, there is a need to specifically examine the role of generative AI within undergraduate biology education. The unique challenges and potential solutions in biology classrooms likely differ from other disciplines like creative writing or computer science. To explore this, I have developed a survey to distribute at SABER 2024. This survey has three aims: 1) Build a community of DBER scholars investigating generative AI applications in undergraduate biology. 2) Identify priorities for professional development on generative AI, for both SABER members and their home institutions. 3) Gather instructor and student perspectives on how generative AI is impacting teaching and learning of biology. I have drafted this survey and welcome feedback from the SABER community to improve it before implementation in the summer of 2024. Beyond gathering data, I hope this survey connects those interested in creatively harnessing the potential of generative AI in this new landscape we find ourselves in.</p>
<embed src="Reuther SABER West 2024 Survey.pdf" type="application/pdf" iframe="" width="100%" height="800">



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{2024,
  author = {},
  title = {Gathering {Perspectives} on {Generative} {AI} in
    {Undergraduate} {Biology} {Education}},
  date = {2024-01-13},
  url = {https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/saberwestsurvey/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
<span>“Gathering Perspectives on Generative AI in Undergraduate Biology
Education.”</span> 2024. January 13, 2024. <a href="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/saberwestsurvey/">https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/saberwestsurvey/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>AI</category>
  <category>Instructors</category>
  <guid>https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/saberwestsurvey/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jan 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/saberwestsurvey/saber.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="64" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Beginner’s Guide to Using AI to Create Canvas Quizzes</title>
  <link>https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/aiquiz2canvas/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/aiquiz2canvas/DALL·E 2023-11-02 16.39.52.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="400"></p>
<figcaption>Created by DALL-E 3</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<em>Bureaucracy is the death of all sound work.</em> - Albert Einstein
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">

</div>
</div>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<h2 id="the-problem" class="anchored">The Problem:</h2>
</blockquote>
<p>Canvas quiz creation can be an incredibly time-consuming and frustrating process. Manually writing questions in Canvas is clunky and soul-draining. While writing questions in a text editor and uploading them seems like an obvious solution, the upload format is prohibitively complicated. The end result is often spending hours awkwardly crafting quiz questions directly in Canvas or desperately trying to rework old quizzes. There has to be a better way to spend your limited prep time.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<h2 id="the-goal" class="anchored">The Goal:</h2>
</blockquote>
<p>Use technology to create/format assessment questions that can be imported to Canvas LMS as a Canvas quiz.</p>
<hr>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<h2 id="prerequisites" class="anchored">Prerequisites</h2>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><p>A list of topics you want covered in your assessment OR assessment questions you have already written.</p></li>
<li><p>A text editor (<a href="https://www.sublimetext.com/">Sublime Text</a>, <a href="https://notepad-plus-plus.org/">Notepad++</a>, or whatever came with your computer)</p></li>
<li><p>Access to <a href="https://chat.openai.com/auth/login">ChatGPT</a> or <a href="https://claude.ai/login?returnTo=%2F">ClaudeAI</a></p></li>
<li><p>A Canvas LMS account.</p></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<h2 id="an-overview" class="anchored">An Overview</h2>
</blockquote>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Use Gen AI to properly format or generate assessment questions.</p></li>
<li><p>Copy the draft into a text editor where you validate for accuracy and quality.</p></li>
<li><p>Upload that text (.txt) file to a <a href="https://text2qti.streamlit.app/">web app</a> I created or convert it locally using the python library found <a href="https://github.com/gpoore/text2qti">here.</a> It will generate a QTI formatted zip file.</p></li>
<li><p>Upload the QTI.zip file to Canvas.</p></li>
</ol>
<hr>
<section id="a-step-by-step-walk-through" class="level1">
<h1>A Step-by-Step Walk-Through</h1>
<section id="part-1-using-generative-ai" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="part-1-using-generative-ai"><strong>Part 1: Using Generative AI</strong></h2>
<section id="what-generative-ai-platform-should-you-use" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-generative-ai-platform-should-you-use"><strong>What generative AI platform should you use?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://chat.openai.com/auth/login">ChatGPT</a> is a good option if you have a pro account and have access to the GPT 4.0 model. The free 3.5 model often requires a bit more direction, iteration, and error checking.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://claude.ai/login?returnTo=%2F">ClaudeAI</a> is a free option that is getting increasingly impressive for a free service. I find it works well for this project.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="using-the-prompt" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="using-the-prompt"><strong>Using the Prompt</strong>:</h4>
<ul>
<li>Copy and paste one of the prompts provided below to the generative AI platform of your choice.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="option-1-you-already-have-questions" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="option-1-you-already-have-questions"><u><em>Option 1: You already have questions</em></u></h4>
<p>Option 1 is if you already have assessment questions and need them formatted for upload to Canvas. Copy and paste (and edit as needed) the prompt below into a gen AI chat.</p>
<details>
<summary>
OPTION 1 PROMPT
</summary>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode markdown wrap code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode markdown"><span id="cb1-1">I have questions that I need properly formatted according to the style guide outlined in this prompt. </span>
<span id="cb1-2">My questions will include the following question types:</span>
<span id="cb1-3"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  - </span>multiple choice questions</span>
<span id="cb1-4"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  - </span>multiple answer questions</span>
<span id="cb1-5"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  - </span>applied or conceptual essay questions </span>
<span id="cb1-6"></span>
<span id="cb1-7">Each question carries a point value of 1. </span>
<span id="cb1-8"></span>
<span id="cb1-9">Your first response should request my drafted quiz questions. You will only modify the formatting as required. Do NOT change the wording of the questions I provide.</span>
<span id="cb1-10"></span>
<span id="cb1-11">Questions must follow the style guide provided:</span>
<span id="cb1-12"></span>
<span id="cb1-13"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1. </span>Use format encapsulated within a code block.</span>
<span id="cb1-14"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">2. </span>Every question should have a title, points value, and an explanation, capturing the persona of a supportive and knowledgeable college biology professor.</span>
<span id="cb1-15"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">3. </span>For multiple choice questions, use "a)", "b)", etc., marking the correct option with an asterisk. Randomly vary which option is correct. It should not always be choice "a)"</span>
<span id="cb1-16"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">4. </span>For multiple answer questions, use "<span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[ ]</span>" for options and "<span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span>" for correct answers.</span>
<span id="cb1-17"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">5. </span>Essay questions should end with a new line that includes "_________". See examples below.</span>
<span id="cb1-18"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">6. </span>Begin every feedback with three dots</span>
<span id="cb1-19"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">7. </span>Questions should only be separated by a line break. Do not add in any extraneous formatting such as "---" between questions.</span>
<span id="cb1-20"></span>
<span id="cb1-21">The quiz's first question should always uphold academic integrity, as shown in the example below.</span>
<span id="cb1-22"></span>
<span id="cb1-23"> Example format in (generate your response entirely within a code block):</span>
<span id="cb1-24"></span>
<span id="cb1-25">Quiz title: Learning Laboratory Techniques: DNA Extraction, PCR, and Gel Electrophoresis</span>
<span id="cb1-26">Quiz description: Review your understanding of DNA extraction, PCR, and gel electrophoresis.</span>
<span id="cb1-27"></span>
<span id="cb1-28">Title: Learn with integrity</span>
<span id="cb1-29">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb1-30"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1. </span>I agree to complete this quiz without the aid of others or AI. I agree not to discuss questions and answers of the quiz until the quiz key is posted. Anything otherwise is a breach of my Academic Integrity and subject to the policies of the University.</span>
<span id="cb1-31">*a) I agree</span>
<span id="cb1-32">b) I disagree</span>
<span id="cb1-33"></span>
<span id="cb1-34">Title: PCR - Mechanism and Reagents</span>
<span id="cb1-35">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb1-36"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">2. </span>Which of the following describes the mechanism of PCR?</span>
<span id="cb1-37">... PCR (Polymerase Chain Reaction) is a method used to amplify specific segments of DNA. It relies on a cycle of denaturation, annealing, and extension. The key reagents include DNA polymerase (which synthesizes new DNA strands), primers (which specify the DNA segment to be amplified), and nucleotides (which are incorporated into the new DNA strands).</span>
<span id="cb1-38">a) PCR breaks down proteins.</span>
<span id="cb1-39">b) PCR translates mRNA into protein.</span>
<span id="cb1-40">*c) PCR amplifies specific DNA segments.</span>
<span id="cb1-41">d) PCR transcribes DNA into RNA.</span>
<span id="cb1-42"></span>
<span id="cb1-43">Title: Gel Electrophoresis - Expected Results and Troubleshooting</span>
<span id="cb1-44">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb1-45"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">3. </span>In gel electrophoresis, what do the expected ladder results look like, and what might an issue with the DNA ladder indicate?</span>
<span id="cb1-46">... Gel electrophoresis separates DNA fragments by size. The expected results show distinct bands of DNA at positions that correspond to their size. The DNA ladder serves as a size marker. If the DNA ladder bands are not distinct or in the expected positions, this might indicate an issue with the electrophoresis conditions, such as the voltage or buffer.</span>
<span id="cb1-47">*a) Expected results show distinct bands of DNA; an issue with the DNA ladder might indicate a problem with the electrophoresis conditions.</span>
<span id="cb1-48">b) Expected results show a single band of DNA; an issue with the DNA ladder might indicate a problem with the PCR reaction.</span>
<span id="cb1-49">c) Expected results show a gradient of color; an issue with the DNA ladder might indicate a problem with the staining process.</span>
<span id="cb1-50">d) Expected results show no visible bands; an issue with the DNA ladder might indicate a problem with the DNA extraction.</span>
<span id="cb1-51"></span>
<span id="cb1-52">Title: DNA - Structure and Replication</span>
<span id="cb1-53">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb1-54"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">4. </span>What aspect of DNA is crucial for its replication in PCR and why?</span>
<span id="cb1-55">... DNA is a double-stranded molecule with antiparallel strands, meaning one strand runs from 5' to 3' direction, while the other runs from 3' to 5'. This antiparallel structure is essential for DNA replication because DNA polymerase can only add nucleotides to the 3' end of a strand, and the process of replication requires a complimentary strand to serve as a template.</span>
<span id="cb1-56">*a) The antiparallel double-stranded structure is crucial because DNA polymerase can only add nucleotides to the 3' end.</span>
<span id="cb1-57">b) The helical structure is crucial because it allows the DNA to be unwound for replication by enzymes.</span>
<span id="cb1-58">c) The presence of histone proteins is crucial because they help to package the new DNA strands.</span>
<span id="cb1-59">d) The sequence of the nucleotides is crucial because it determines how negatively charged the DNA is.</span>
<span id="cb1-60"></span>
<span id="cb1-61">Title: DNA - Complimentary Base Pairing</span>
<span id="cb1-62">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb1-63"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">5. </span>If one strand of DNA has the sequence 5'-ATGCGTA-3', what would be the sequence of the complimentary strand?</span>
<span id="cb1-64">... In DNA, adenine (A) pairs with thymine (T), and guanine (G) pairs with cytosine (C). Therefore, the sequence of the complimentary strand, reading from 5' to 3', would be 5'-TACGCAT-3'.</span>
<span id="cb1-65">a) 3'-TACGCAT-5'</span>
<span id="cb1-66">b) 5'-ATGCGTA-3'</span>
<span id="cb1-67">*c) 5'-TACGCAT-3'</span>
<span id="cb1-68">d) 5'-CATGCGT-3'</span>
<span id="cb1-69"></span>
<span id="cb1-70">Title: PCR - Expected Results</span>
<span id="cb1-71">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb1-72"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">6. </span>In a successful PCR reaction, what should the results look like when visualized on a gel?</span>
<span id="cb1-73">... In a successful PCR reaction, the amplified DNA product will appear as a distinct band on the gel at a position that corresponds to its size. The exact position can be determined using a DNA ladder.</span>
<span id="cb1-74">*a) A distinct band at a position that corresponds to the size of the amplified DNA segment.</span>
<span id="cb1-75">b) Multiple bands at various positions.</span>
<span id="cb1-76">c) A gradient of color throughout the gel.</span>
<span id="cb1-77">d) No visible bands.</span>
<span id="cb1-78"></span>
<span id="cb1-79">Title: PCR - Reagents</span>
<span id="cb1-80">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb1-81"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">7. </span>In a PCR reaction, which of the following reagents are required?</span>
<span id="cb1-82">... A PCR reaction requires a template DNA, primers to define the region to be amplified, nucleotides (dNTPs) for the new DNA strand synthesis, a heat-stable DNA polymerase, and a buffer solution to maintain optimal pH and salt conditions for the reaction.</span>
<span id="cb1-83"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Template DNA</span>
<span id="cb1-84"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Primers</span>
<span id="cb1-85"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> dNTPs</span>
<span id="cb1-86"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> DNA Polymerase</span>
<span id="cb1-87"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[ ]</span> RNA Polymerase</span>
<span id="cb1-88"></span>
<span id="cb1-89">Title: Gel Electrophoresis - Components</span>
<span id="cb1-90">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb1-91"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">8. </span>What are the necessary components to set up a gel electrophoresis experiment?</span>
<span id="cb1-92">... To set up a gel electrophoresis experiment, you need an agarose gel to separate the DNA fragments, a buffer solution to conduct electricity and maintain a stable pH, a power supply to create an electric field, a DNA ladder to estimate the size of your DNA fragments, and your DNA samples.</span>
<span id="cb1-93"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Agarose gel</span>
<span id="cb1-94"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Buffer solution</span>
<span id="cb1-95"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Power supply</span>
<span id="cb1-96"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> DNA ladder</span>
<span id="cb1-97"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> DNA samples</span>
<span id="cb1-98"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[ ]</span> dNTPs</span>
<span id="cb1-99"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[ ]</span> Primers</span>
<span id="cb1-100"></span>
<span id="cb1-101">Title: Troubleshooting in PCR</span>
<span id="cb1-102">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb1-103"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">9. </span>If a PCR reaction does not yield the expected product, which of the following could be possible reasons?</span>
<span id="cb1-104">... Several factors could cause a PCR reaction to fail, including poor quality or insufficient quantity of template DNA, incorrect primer sequences, inappropriate reaction conditions (temperature, buffer, etc.), or issues with the DNA polymerase.</span>
<span id="cb1-105"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Poor quality or insufficient quantity of template DNA</span>
<span id="cb1-106"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Incorrect primer sequences</span>
<span id="cb1-107"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Inappropriate reaction conditions</span>
<span id="cb1-108"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[ ]</span> Contamination in the DNA ladder</span>
<span id="cb1-109"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Issues with the DNA polymerase</span>
<span id="cb1-110"></span>
<span id="cb1-111">Title: Controls in Experiments</span>
<span id="cb1-112">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb1-113"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">10. </span>Discuss the importance of positive and negative controls in an experimental setup such as PCR. Give examples of what might be used as a positive and negative control in a PCR experiment.</span>
<span id="cb1-114">... Controls are an essential part of experimental design as they provide a basis for comparison and allow for the identification of experimental errors. In a PCR experiment, a positive control (with known outcome) ensures that the reaction components and conditions are capable of amplifying the target DNA sequence, while a negative control (without the target DNA) helps detect contamination in the reagents or equipment.</span>
<span id="cb1-115">_________</span>
<span id="cb1-116"></span>
<span id="cb1-117">Title: Data Analysis in Biology</span>
<span id="cb1-118">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb1-119"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">11. </span>Explain why exploratory data analysis is an essential step before diving into statistical testing.</span>
<span id="cb1-120">... Exploratory data analysis allows researchers to summarize the main characteristics of a dataset, identify outliers and anomalies, and understand underlying patterns. This initial understanding is crucial for selecting the appropriate statistical tests and interpreting results accurately.</span>
<span id="cb1-121">_________ </span>
<span id="cb1-122"></span>
<span id="cb1-123">Title: Understanding False Positives and Negatives</span>
<span id="cb1-124">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb1-125"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">12. </span>Discuss the implications of false positives and negatives in medical diagnostics.</span>
<span id="cb1-126">... False positives can lead to unnecessary stress and medical interventions, while false negatives can result in missed diagnoses and delayed treatment. Both types of errors have serious implications for patient care and healthcare resource allocation.</span>
<span id="cb1-127">_________ </span>
<span id="cb1-128"></span>
<span id="cb1-129">Title: Lab Techniques</span>
<span id="cb1-130">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb1-131"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">13. </span>List two techniques you learned in the lab that aided your understanding of the subject matter and explain how they did so.</span>
<span id="cb1-132">... Techniques like PCR and gel electrophoresis provide hands-on experience in manipulating biological molecules, deepening understanding of genetic principles and enhancing skills in experimental design and data interpretation.</span>
<span id="cb1-133">_________ </span></code></pre></div>
</details></section>
<section id="option-2-ai-generated-questions" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="option-2-ai-generated-questions"><u><em>Option 2: AI generated questions</em></u></h4>
<p>Option 2 is if you want gen AI to generate questions for you. Copy and paste (and edit as needed) the prompt below into a gen AI chat.</p>
<details>
<summary>
OPTION 2 PROMPT
</summary>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb2" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode markdown wrap code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode markdown"><span id="cb2-1">Design a compelling online quiz tailored for an undergraduate biology course, emphasizing higher-order cognitive skills based on Bloom's taxonomy. The quiz should comprise:</span>
<span id="cb2-2"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">- </span>10 multiple choice questions</span>
<span id="cb2-3"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">- </span>10 multiple answer questions</span>
<span id="cb2-4"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">- </span>5 applied or conceptual essay questions </span>
<span id="cb2-5"></span>
<span id="cb2-6">Each question carries a point value of 1. Ensure questions are not based on mere factual recall. Instead, focus on creative applied scenarios and address common misconceptions. Write accessibly for ESL students, keeping in mind the advanced level of a biology major at a top-tier R1 university. </span>
<span id="cb2-7"></span>
<span id="cb2-8">Your first response should request a list of topics from me in the form of a list.</span>
<span id="cb2-9"></span>
<span id="cb2-10">Questions must follow the style guide provided:</span>
<span id="cb2-11"></span>
<span id="cb2-12"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1. </span>Use format encapsulated within a code block.</span>
<span id="cb2-13"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">2. </span>Every question should have a title, points value, and an explanation, capturing the persona of a supportive and knowledgeable college biology professor.</span>
<span id="cb2-14"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">3. </span>For multiple choice questions, use "a)", "b)", etc., marking the correct option with an asterisk. Randomly vary which option is correct. It should not always be choice "a)"</span>
<span id="cb2-15"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">4. </span>For multiple answer questions, use "<span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[ ]</span>" for options and "<span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span>" for correct answers.</span>
<span id="cb2-16"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">5. </span>Essay questions should end with a new line that includes "_________". See examples below.</span>
<span id="cb2-17"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">6. </span>Begin every feedback with three dots</span>
<span id="cb2-18"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">7. </span>Questions should only be separated by a line break. Do not add in any extraneous formatting such as "---" between questions.</span>
<span id="cb2-19"></span>
<span id="cb2-20">The quiz's first question should always uphold academic integrity, as shown in the example below.</span>
<span id="cb2-21"></span>
<span id="cb2-22"></span>
<span id="cb2-23">Example format in (generate your response entirely within a code block):</span>
<span id="cb2-24"></span>
<span id="cb2-25">Quiz title: Learning Laboratory Techniques: DNA Extraction, PCR, and Gel Electrophoresis</span>
<span id="cb2-26">Quiz description: Review your understanding of DNA extraction, PCR, and gel electrophoresis.</span>
<span id="cb2-27"></span>
<span id="cb2-28">Title: Learn with integrity</span>
<span id="cb2-29">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb2-30"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1. </span>I agree to complete this quiz without the aid of others or AI. I agree not to discuss questions and answers of the quiz until the quiz key is posted. Anything otherwise is a breach of my Academic Integrity and subject to the policies of the University.</span>
<span id="cb2-31">*a) I agree</span>
<span id="cb2-32">b) I disagree</span>
<span id="cb2-33"></span>
<span id="cb2-34">Title: PCR - Mechanism and Reagents</span>
<span id="cb2-35">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb2-36"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">2. </span>Which of the following describes the mechanism of PCR?</span>
<span id="cb2-37">... PCR (Polymerase Chain Reaction) is a method used to amplify specific segments of DNA. It relies on a cycle of denaturation, annealing, and extension. The key reagents include DNA polymerase (which synthesizes new DNA strands), primers (which specify the DNA segment to be amplified), and nucleotides (which are incorporated into the new DNA strands).</span>
<span id="cb2-38">a) PCR breaks down proteins.</span>
<span id="cb2-39">b) PCR translates mRNA into protein.</span>
<span id="cb2-40">*c) PCR amplifies specific DNA segments.</span>
<span id="cb2-41">d) PCR transcribes DNA into RNA.</span>
<span id="cb2-42"></span>
<span id="cb2-43">Title: Gel Electrophoresis - Expected Results and Troubleshooting</span>
<span id="cb2-44">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb2-45"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">3. </span>In gel electrophoresis, what do the expected ladder results look like, and what might an issue with the DNA ladder indicate?</span>
<span id="cb2-46">... Gel electrophoresis separates DNA fragments by size. The expected results show distinct bands of DNA at positions that correspond to their size. The DNA ladder serves as a size marker. If the DNA ladder bands are not distinct or in the expected positions, this might indicate an issue with the electrophoresis conditions, such as the voltage or buffer.</span>
<span id="cb2-47">*a) Expected results show distinct bands of DNA; an issue with the DNA ladder might indicate a problem with the electrophoresis conditions.</span>
<span id="cb2-48">b) Expected results show a single band of DNA; an issue with the DNA ladder might indicate a problem with the PCR reaction.</span>
<span id="cb2-49">c) Expected results show a gradient of color; an issue with the DNA ladder might indicate a problem with the staining process.</span>
<span id="cb2-50">d) Expected results show no visible bands; an issue with the DNA ladder might indicate a problem with the DNA extraction.</span>
<span id="cb2-51"></span>
<span id="cb2-52">Title: DNA - Structure and Replication</span>
<span id="cb2-53">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb2-54"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">4. </span>What aspect of DNA is crucial for its replication in PCR and why?</span>
<span id="cb2-55">... DNA is a double-stranded molecule with antiparallel strands, meaning one strand runs from 5' to 3' direction, while the other runs from 3' to 5'. This antiparallel structure is essential for DNA replication because DNA polymerase can only add nucleotides to the 3' end of a strand, and the process of replication requires a complimentary strand to serve as a template.</span>
<span id="cb2-56">*a) The antiparallel double-stranded structure is crucial because DNA polymerase can only add nucleotides to the 3' end.</span>
<span id="cb2-57">b) The helical structure is crucial because it allows the DNA to be unwound for replication by enzymes.</span>
<span id="cb2-58">c) The presence of histone proteins is crucial because they help to package the new DNA strands.</span>
<span id="cb2-59">d) The sequence of the nucleotides is crucial because it determines how negatively charged the DNA is.</span>
<span id="cb2-60"></span>
<span id="cb2-61">Title: DNA - Complimentary Base Pairing</span>
<span id="cb2-62">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb2-63"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">5. </span>If one strand of DNA has the sequence 5'-ATGCGTA-3', what would be the sequence of the complimentary strand?</span>
<span id="cb2-64">... In DNA, adenine (A) pairs with thymine (T), and guanine (G) pairs with cytosine (C). Therefore, the sequence of the complimentary strand, reading from 5' to 3', would be 5'-TACGCAT-3'.</span>
<span id="cb2-65">a) 3'-TACGCAT-5'</span>
<span id="cb2-66">b) 5'-ATGCGTA-3'</span>
<span id="cb2-67">*c) 5'-TACGCAT-3'</span>
<span id="cb2-68">d) 5'-CATGCGT-3'</span>
<span id="cb2-69"></span>
<span id="cb2-70">Title: PCR - Expected Results</span>
<span id="cb2-71">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb2-72"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">6. </span>In a successful PCR reaction, what should the results look like when visualized on a gel?</span>
<span id="cb2-73">... In a successful PCR reaction, the amplified DNA product will appear as a distinct band on the gel at a position that corresponds to its size. The exact position can be determined using a DNA ladder.</span>
<span id="cb2-74">*a) A distinct band at a position that corresponds to the size of the amplified DNA segment.</span>
<span id="cb2-75">b) Multiple bands at various positions.</span>
<span id="cb2-76">c) A gradient of color throughout the gel.</span>
<span id="cb2-77">d) No visible bands.</span>
<span id="cb2-78"></span>
<span id="cb2-79">Title: PCR - Reagents</span>
<span id="cb2-80">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb2-81"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">7. </span>In a PCR reaction, which of the following reagents are required?</span>
<span id="cb2-82">... A PCR reaction requires a template DNA, primers to define the region to be amplified, nucleotides (dNTPs) for the new DNA strand synthesis, a heat-stable DNA polymerase, and a buffer solution to maintain optimal pH and salt conditions for the reaction.</span>
<span id="cb2-83"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Template DNA</span>
<span id="cb2-84"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Primers</span>
<span id="cb2-85"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> dNTPs</span>
<span id="cb2-86"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> DNA Polymerase</span>
<span id="cb2-87"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[ ]</span> RNA Polymerase</span>
<span id="cb2-88"></span>
<span id="cb2-89">Title: Gel Electrophoresis - Components</span>
<span id="cb2-90">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb2-91"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">8. </span>What are the necessary components to set up a gel electrophoresis experiment?</span>
<span id="cb2-92">... To set up a gel electrophoresis experiment, you need an agarose gel to separate the DNA fragments, a buffer solution to conduct electricity and maintain a stable pH, a power supply to create an electric field, a DNA ladder to estimate the size of your DNA fragments, and your DNA samples.</span>
<span id="cb2-93"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Agarose gel</span>
<span id="cb2-94"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Buffer solution</span>
<span id="cb2-95"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Power supply</span>
<span id="cb2-96"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> DNA ladder</span>
<span id="cb2-97"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> DNA samples</span>
<span id="cb2-98"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[ ]</span> dNTPs</span>
<span id="cb2-99"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[ ]</span> Primers</span>
<span id="cb2-100"></span>
<span id="cb2-101">Title: Troubleshooting in PCR</span>
<span id="cb2-102">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb2-103"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">9. </span>If a PCR reaction does not yield the expected product, which of the following could be possible reasons?</span>
<span id="cb2-104">... Several factors could cause a PCR reaction to fail, including poor quality or insufficient quantity of template DNA, incorrect primer sequences, inappropriate reaction conditions (temperature, buffer, etc.), or issues with the DNA polymerase.</span>
<span id="cb2-105"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Poor quality or insufficient quantity of template DNA</span>
<span id="cb2-106"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Incorrect primer sequences</span>
<span id="cb2-107"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Inappropriate reaction conditions</span>
<span id="cb2-108"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[ ]</span> Contamination in the DNA ladder</span>
<span id="cb2-109"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Issues with the DNA polymerase</span>
<span id="cb2-110"></span>
<span id="cb2-111">Title: Controls in Experiments</span>
<span id="cb2-112">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb2-113"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">10. </span>Discuss the importance of positive and negative controls in an experimental setup such as PCR. Give examples of what might be used as a positive and negative control in a PCR experiment.</span>
<span id="cb2-114">... Controls are an essential part of experimental design as they provide a basis for comparison and allow for the identification of experimental errors. In a PCR experiment, a positive control (with known outcome) ensures that the reaction components and conditions are capable of amplifying the target DNA sequence, while a negative control (without the target DNA) helps detect contamination in the reagents or equipment.</span>
<span id="cb2-115">_________</span>
<span id="cb2-116"></span>
<span id="cb2-117">Title: Data Analysis in Biology</span>
<span id="cb2-118">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb2-119"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">11. </span>Explain why exploratory data analysis is an essential step before diving into statistical testing.</span>
<span id="cb2-120">... Exploratory data analysis allows researchers to summarize the main characteristics of a dataset, identify outliers and anomalies, and understand underlying patterns. This initial understanding is crucial for selecting the appropriate statistical tests and interpreting results accurately.</span>
<span id="cb2-121">_________ </span>
<span id="cb2-122"></span>
<span id="cb2-123">Title: Understanding False Positives and Negatives</span>
<span id="cb2-124">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb2-125"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">12. </span>Discuss the implications of false positives and negatives in medical diagnostics.</span>
<span id="cb2-126">... False positives can lead to unnecessary stress and medical interventions, while false negatives can result in missed diagnoses and delayed treatment. Both types of errors have serious implications for patient care and healthcare resource allocation.</span>
<span id="cb2-127">_________ </span>
<span id="cb2-128"></span>
<span id="cb2-129">Title: Lab Techniques</span>
<span id="cb2-130">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb2-131"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">13. </span>List two techniques you learned in the lab that aided your understanding of the subject matter and explain how they did so.</span>
<span id="cb2-132">... Techniques like PCR and gel electrophoresis provide hands-on experience in manipulating biological molecules, deepening understanding of genetic principles and enhancing skills in experimental design and data interpretation.</span>
<span id="cb2-133">_________ </span></code></pre></div>
</details>
</section>
<section id="option-3-the-no-ai-option" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="option-3-the-no-ai-option"><u><strong><em>Option 3: The no AI option</em></strong></u></h4>
<p>If you already have questions and only need to format them for conversion, you can do the process manually without the use of any gen AI.</p>
<p>Conduct all of your reformatting in a text editor. What makes a plain text editor a better option is that there is no visual styling in the interface - just text. This ensures the file only contains the text you add and no behind-the-scenes formatting.</p>
<p>Use the style guide found <a href="https://github.com/gpoore/text2qti#readme">here</a> (the more detailed option). You may also check out the example style I have created below (the simpler option)</p>
<details>
<summary>
OPTION 3 STYLE GUIDE
</summary>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb3" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode markdown wrap code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode markdown"><span id="cb3-1"><span class="in" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">    Questions must follow the style guide provided:</span></span>
<span id="cb3-2"></span>
<span id="cb3-3"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1. </span>Every question should have a title, points value, and an explanation.</span>
<span id="cb3-4"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">2. </span>For multiple choice questions, use "a)", "b)", etc., marking the correct option with an asterisk. Randomly vary which option is correct. It should not always be choice "a)"</span>
<span id="cb3-5"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">3. </span>For multiple answer questions, use "<span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[ ]</span>" for options and "<span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span>" for correct answers.</span>
<span id="cb3-6"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">4. </span>Essay questions should end with a new line that includes "_________". See examples below.</span>
<span id="cb3-7"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">5. </span>Begin every feedback with three dots</span>
<span id="cb3-8"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">6. </span>Questions should only be separated by a line break. Do not add in any extraneous formatting such as "---" between questions.</span>
<span id="cb3-9"></span>
<span id="cb3-10">Example format in (generate your response entirely within a code block):</span>
<span id="cb3-11"></span>
<span id="cb3-12">Quiz title: Learning Laboratory Techniques: DNA Extraction, PCR, and Gel Electrophoresis</span>
<span id="cb3-13">Quiz description: Review your understanding of DNA extraction, PCR, and gel electrophoresis.</span>
<span id="cb3-14"></span>
<span id="cb3-15">Title: Learn with integrity</span>
<span id="cb3-16">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb3-17"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1. </span>I agree to complete this quiz without the aid of others or AI. I agree not to discuss questions and answers of the quiz until the quiz key is posted. Anything otherwise is a breach of my Academic Integrity and subject to the policies of the University.</span>
<span id="cb3-18">*a) I agree</span>
<span id="cb3-19">b) I disagree</span>
<span id="cb3-20"></span>
<span id="cb3-21">Title: PCR - Mechanism and Reagents</span>
<span id="cb3-22">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb3-23"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">2. </span>Which of the following describes the mechanism of PCR?</span>
<span id="cb3-24">... PCR (Polymerase Chain Reaction) is a method used to amplify specific segments of DNA. It relies on a cycle of denaturation, annealing, and extension. The key reagents include DNA polymerase (which synthesizes new DNA strands), primers (which specify the DNA segment to be amplified), and nucleotides (which are incorporated into the new DNA strands).</span>
<span id="cb3-25">a) PCR breaks down proteins.</span>
<span id="cb3-26">b) PCR translates mRNA into protein.</span>
<span id="cb3-27">*c) PCR amplifies specific DNA segments.</span>
<span id="cb3-28">d) PCR transcribes DNA into RNA.</span>
<span id="cb3-29"></span>
<span id="cb3-30">Title: Gel Electrophoresis - Expected Results and Troubleshooting</span>
<span id="cb3-31">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb3-32"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">3. </span>In gel electrophoresis, what do the expected ladder results look like, and what might an issue with the DNA ladder indicate?</span>
<span id="cb3-33">... Gel electrophoresis separates DNA fragments by size. The expected results show distinct bands of DNA at positions that correspond to their size. The DNA ladder serves as a size marker. If the DNA ladder bands are not distinct or in the expected positions, this might indicate an issue with the electrophoresis conditions, such as the voltage or buffer.</span>
<span id="cb3-34">*a) Expected results show distinct bands of DNA; an issue with the DNA ladder might indicate a problem with the electrophoresis conditions.</span>
<span id="cb3-35">b) Expected results show a single band of DNA; an issue with the DNA ladder might indicate a problem with the PCR reaction.</span>
<span id="cb3-36">c) Expected results show a gradient of color; an issue with the DNA ladder might indicate a problem with the staining process.</span>
<span id="cb3-37">d) Expected results show no visible bands; an issue with the DNA ladder might indicate a problem with the DNA extraction.</span>
<span id="cb3-38"></span>
<span id="cb3-39">Title: DNA - Structure and Replication</span>
<span id="cb3-40">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb3-41"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">4. </span>What aspect of DNA is crucial for its replication in PCR and why?</span>
<span id="cb3-42">... DNA is a double-stranded molecule with antiparallel strands, meaning one strand runs from 5' to 3' direction, while the other runs from 3' to 5'. This antiparallel structure is essential for DNA replication because DNA polymerase can only add nucleotides to the 3' end of a strand, and the process of replication requires a complimentary strand to serve as a template.</span>
<span id="cb3-43">*a) The antiparallel double-stranded structure is crucial because DNA polymerase can only add nucleotides to the 3' end.</span>
<span id="cb3-44">b) The helical structure is crucial because it allows the DNA to be unwound for replication by enzymes.</span>
<span id="cb3-45">c) The presence of histone proteins is crucial because they help to package the new DNA strands.</span>
<span id="cb3-46">d) The sequence of the nucleotides is crucial because it determines how negatively charged the DNA is.</span>
<span id="cb3-47"></span>
<span id="cb3-48">Title: DNA - Complimentary Base Pairing</span>
<span id="cb3-49">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb3-50"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">5. </span>If one strand of DNA has the sequence 5'-ATGCGTA-3', what would be the sequence of the complimentary strand?</span>
<span id="cb3-51">... In DNA, adenine (A) pairs with thymine (T), and guanine (G) pairs with cytosine (C). Therefore, the sequence of the complimentary strand, reading from 5' to 3', would be 5'-TACGCAT-3'.</span>
<span id="cb3-52">a) 3'-TACGCAT-5'</span>
<span id="cb3-53">b) 5'-ATGCGTA-3'</span>
<span id="cb3-54">*c) 5'-TACGCAT-3'</span>
<span id="cb3-55">d) 5'-CATGCGT-3'</span>
<span id="cb3-56"></span>
<span id="cb3-57">Title: PCR - Expected Results</span>
<span id="cb3-58">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb3-59"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">6. </span>In a successful PCR reaction, what should the results look like when visualized on a gel?</span>
<span id="cb3-60">... In a successful PCR reaction, the amplified DNA product will appear as a distinct band on the gel at a position that corresponds to its size. The exact position can be determined using a DNA ladder.</span>
<span id="cb3-61">*a) A distinct band at a position that corresponds to the size of the amplified DNA segment.</span>
<span id="cb3-62">b) Multiple bands at various positions.</span>
<span id="cb3-63">c) A gradient of color throughout the gel.</span>
<span id="cb3-64">d) No visible bands.</span>
<span id="cb3-65"></span>
<span id="cb3-66">Title: PCR - Reagents</span>
<span id="cb3-67">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb3-68"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">7. </span>In a PCR reaction, which of the following reagents are required?</span>
<span id="cb3-69">... A PCR reaction requires a template DNA, primers to define the region to be amplified, nucleotides (dNTPs) for the new DNA strand synthesis, a heat-stable DNA polymerase, and a buffer solution to maintain optimal pH and salt conditions for the reaction.</span>
<span id="cb3-70"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Template DNA</span>
<span id="cb3-71"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Primers</span>
<span id="cb3-72"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> dNTPs</span>
<span id="cb3-73"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> DNA Polymerase</span>
<span id="cb3-74"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[ ]</span> RNA Polymerase</span>
<span id="cb3-75"></span>
<span id="cb3-76">Title: Gel Electrophoresis - Components</span>
<span id="cb3-77">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb3-78"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">8. </span>What are the necessary components to set up a gel electrophoresis experiment?</span>
<span id="cb3-79">... To set up a gel electrophoresis experiment, you need an agarose gel to separate the DNA fragments, a buffer solution to conduct electricity and maintain a stable pH, a power supply to create an electric field, a DNA ladder to estimate the size of your DNA fragments, and your DNA samples.</span>
<span id="cb3-80"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Agarose gel</span>
<span id="cb3-81"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Buffer solution</span>
<span id="cb3-82"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Power supply</span>
<span id="cb3-83"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> DNA ladder</span>
<span id="cb3-84"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> DNA samples</span>
<span id="cb3-85"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[ ]</span> dNTPs</span>
<span id="cb3-86"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[ ]</span> Primers</span>
<span id="cb3-87"></span>
<span id="cb3-88">Title: Troubleshooting in PCR</span>
<span id="cb3-89">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb3-90"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">9. </span>If a PCR reaction does not yield the expected product, which of the following could be possible reasons?</span>
<span id="cb3-91">... Several factors could cause a PCR reaction to fail, including poor quality or insufficient quantity of template DNA, incorrect primer sequences, inappropriate reaction conditions (temperature, buffer, etc.), or issues with the DNA polymerase.</span>
<span id="cb3-92"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Poor quality or insufficient quantity of template DNA</span>
<span id="cb3-93"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Incorrect primer sequences</span>
<span id="cb3-94"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Inappropriate reaction conditions</span>
<span id="cb3-95"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[ ]</span> Contamination in the DNA ladder</span>
<span id="cb3-96"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">[</span><span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">]</span> Issues with the DNA polymerase</span>
<span id="cb3-97"></span>
<span id="cb3-98">Title: Controls in Experiments</span>
<span id="cb3-99">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb3-100"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">10. </span>Discuss the importance of positive and negative controls in an experimental setup such as PCR. Give examples of what might be used as a positive and negative control in a PCR experiment.</span>
<span id="cb3-101">... Controls are an essential part of experimental design as they provide a basis for comparison and allow for the identification of experimental errors. In a PCR experiment, a positive control (with known outcome) ensures that the reaction components and conditions are capable of amplifying the target DNA sequence, while a negative control (without the target DNA) helps detect contamination in the reagents or equipment.</span>
<span id="cb3-102">_________</span>
<span id="cb3-103"></span>
<span id="cb3-104">Title: Data Analysis in Biology</span>
<span id="cb3-105">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb3-106"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">11. </span>Explain why exploratory data analysis is an essential step before diving into statistical testing.</span>
<span id="cb3-107">... Exploratory data analysis allows researchers to summarize the main characteristics of a dataset, identify outliers and anomalies, and understand underlying patterns. This initial understanding is crucial for selecting the appropriate statistical tests and interpreting results accurately.</span>
<span id="cb3-108">_________ </span>
<span id="cb3-109"></span>
<span id="cb3-110">Title: Understanding False Positives and Negatives</span>
<span id="cb3-111">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb3-112"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">12. </span>Discuss the implications of false positives and negatives in medical diagnostics.</span>
<span id="cb3-113">... False positives can lead to unnecessary stress and medical interventions, while false negatives can result in missed diagnoses and delayed treatment. Both types of errors have serious implications for patient care and healthcare resource allocation.</span>
<span id="cb3-114">_________ </span>
<span id="cb3-115"></span>
<span id="cb3-116">Title: Lab Techniques</span>
<span id="cb3-117">Points: 1</span>
<span id="cb3-118"><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">13. </span>List two techniques you learned in the lab that aided your understanding of the subject matter and explain how they did so.</span>
<span id="cb3-119">... Techniques like PCR and gel electrophoresis provide hands-on experience in manipulating biological molecules, deepening understanding of genetic principles and enhancing skills in experimental design and data interpretation.</span>
<span id="cb3-120">_________ </span></code></pre></div>
</details>
<hr>
</section>
</section>
<section id="part-2-verify-verify-verify" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="part-2-verify-verify-verify"><strong>Part 2: Verify, verify, verify</strong></h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>ALWAYS</strong> verify the accuracy of the information produced by gen AI. It will frequently produce bad questions and false information. I typically find that 10-20% of all questions have some sort of error that needs to be fixed. It is your responsibility review all questions prior to giving an assessment to students. Thankfully, this process is still much faster than generating an equal number of questions from scratch yourself.</p>
</blockquote>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Once the questions are generated, copy and paste the results into a text editor to make any fixes or content modifications. Any text editor such as <a href="https://www.sublimetext.com/">Sublime Text</a>, <a href="https://notepad-plus-plus.org/">Notepad++</a>, or whatever came with your computer will suffice.</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Note: Be wary of using Microsoft Word or Google Documents. This needs to be a perfectly formatted .txt file and the more complex the software, the more likely it will add extraneous formatting</em></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Edit the document and verify the accuracy and content of the quiz. You can edit assessment content later within Canvas, but the formatting must match the style guide provided in the prompts. A more comprehensive style sheet can be found <a href="https://github.com/gpoore/text2qti#readme">here</a> if needed.</p></li>
<li><p>You can also add any of your own original questions to the text file, as long as you format them properly.</p></li>
<li><p>Save the document as a “.txt” file. This is what you will be converting in the next part.</p></li>
</ol>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="part-3-converting-questions-to-qti.zip-format" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="part-3-converting-questions-to-qti.zip-format"><strong>Part 3:</strong> Converting Questions to qti.zip Format</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>This app, based on the <a href="https://github.com/gpoore/text2qti">text2qti python library</a>, will convert the markdown formatted questions into a qti.zip file compatible with Canvas LMS.</p>
<p><a class="btn btn-primary" href="https://text2qti.streamlit.app/">Click here to visit the web app</a></p>
<p>You may need to “wake up” the app by clicking a button. This is normal.</p></li>
<li><p>Drag and drop or select your quiz text (.txt) file. Click to convert.</p></li>
<li><p>If there are errors generated, see if the error indicates the line # of the formatting error.</p>
<ul>
<li>The most common errors include:
<ul>
<li>AI incorrectly formatting the order of question title, points, feedback, and question.</li>
<li>AI not including a ‘__________’ on the line immediately after any essay questions.</li>
<li>AI incorrectly formatting the correct answers for multiple choice, which should be ‘*b)’ with no space in-between.</li>
<li>AI incorrectly formatting multiple answer questions. Correct options must be ‘[*]’ and incorrect options must be ‘[ ]’ with 1 space in-between the brackets.</li>
<li>It is also helpful if the ‘.txt’ file name has no spaces in it and is short. A good example of a name could be ‘quiz_3.txt’</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>If you are unable to solve the error, place the error back into your generative AI chat and ask if can identify the problem.</p></li>
<li><p>Download the generated .zip file to your computer.</p></li>
</ol>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="part-4-uploading-the-qti.zip-file-to-canvas" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="part-4-uploading-the-qti.zip-file-to-canvas"><strong>Part 4:</strong> Uploading the qti.zip file to Canvas</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Log in to your Canvas LMS account.</p></li>
<li><p>Navigate to the course where you want to upload the quiz.</p></li>
<li><p>On your ‘Home” page, select the ’Import Existing Content’ button in the upper right.</p></li>
<li><p>In the drop-down bar, select ‘QTI .zip file’ and choose ‘Create New Question Bank’ in the drop-down and choose an appropriate name.</p></li>
<li><p>Select ‘Import’</p></li>
<li><p>Navigate to the ‘Quizzes’ Menu and edit and publish your new quiz as desired. You’re done!</p></li>
</ol>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="part-5-watch-the-video-walk-through" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="part-5-watch-the-video-walk-through">Part 5: Watch the Video Walk-through</h2>
<p><a href="https://youtu.be/CnOmRkzb-zA">A Beginner's Guide to Using AI to Create Canvas Quizzes</a></p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/CnOmRkzb-zA?si=5Zf0sjGmTNhdIrTj" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="additional-resources" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="additional-resources">Additional Resources</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="chatgpt_link_here">ChatGPT Official Documentation</a></li>
<li><a href="streamlit_link_here">Streamlit Documentation</a></li>
<li><a href="canvas_lms_link_here">Canvas LMS Help Center</a></li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{2023,
  author = {},
  title = {A {Beginner’s} {Guide} to {Using} {AI} to {Create} {Canvas}
    {Quizzes}},
  date = {2023-10-22},
  url = {https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/aiquiz2canvas/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
<span>“A Beginner’s Guide to Using AI to Create Canvas Quizzes.”</span>
2023. October 22, 2023. <a href="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/aiquiz2canvas/">https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/aiquiz2canvas/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/aiquiz2canvas/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Incorporating a Mentorship Plan into Your Degree</title>
  <dc:creator>Allison Kifer</dc:creator>
  <link>https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/mentormosaic2/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>While many aspects of a degree are well planned, mentorship is an aspect that is often overlooked.</p>
<p><img src="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/mentormosaic2/Header_Image.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<section id="incorporating-a-mentorship-plan-into-your-degree" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="incorporating-a-mentorship-plan-into-your-degree"><strong>Incorporating a Mentorship Plan into Your Degree</strong></h2>
<p>It wasn’t until halfway through my master’s program at UC San Diego did I realize I needed to create an adaptive mentorship plan. In order to graduate and feel confident going into the working world outside of my master’s, I needed to receive extra support.&nbsp;</p>
<p>I was in the expedited BS/MS program, which combined a year’s worth of research at a lab on campus in my BS with another year’s worth of research in my MS. Because it was a degree in biology, this meant that my research would culminate in a final written and oral thesis defense.&nbsp;</p>
<p>I had comfortably stayed at my undergraduate lab for my master’s, and while my location did not change, the expectation for my work had.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The next year of my master’s was going to be rigorous, as my experiments were longer and required more attention, and I was a bit terrified to present my research among academics. My postdoctoral mentor had also recently left the lab and with that my primary person for direct technical guidance and career advice was no longer as easily accessible.&nbsp;</p>
<p>It was hard to admit at the time, but I was treading in deep, deep water. I was unsure how to navigate this all with less support than I had before.&nbsp;</p>
<p><img src="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/mentormosaic2/Image_1.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Because of my experiences with mentorship in the past, I recognized that I needed extended support and some clarity within the mentorship I already had.</p>
<section id="if-you-are-asked-to-tackle-larger-responsibilities-and-your-abilities-are-stretched-thin-your-support-system-will-need-to-step-up." class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="if-you-are-asked-to-tackle-larger-responsibilities-and-your-abilities-are-stretched-thin-your-support-system-will-need-to-step-up."><em>If you are asked to tackle larger responsibilities and your abilities are stretched thin, your support system will need to step up.</em></h4>
<p>And because everyone is busy and has many responsibilities of their own, the only person that can catalyze this is you. Rather than expend your energy trying to cover all your bases, an investment into a mentorship plan will help tremendously.&nbsp;</p>
</section>
<section id="how-does-one-successfully-create-a-mentorship-plan" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-does-one-successfully-create-a-mentorship-plan"><strong>How does one successfully create a mentorship plan?</strong></h3>
<p>Firstly, it is important to differentiate a research plan from a mentorship plan. Similar to many other research-based MS programs, I submitted a research proposal during my application process. A research proposal outlines what types of experiments you will be conducting in order to answer a set of scientific questions, and how you might achieve these goals throughout your academic timeline. While it is easy for you to think your research proposal encompasses your mentorship plan, this is not the case.&nbsp;</p>
<p>A mentorship plan recognizes the mentors that you currently have (professors, postdocs, TAs, peers etc) and what they are capable of assisting you with. From there, you may notice the gaps of support where you need it most. Much of my own anxiety from graduate school stemmed from the feeling of trying incredibly hard and still failing. This made me believe that “my best” was never going to be good enough, and that I might not complete what I had set to achieve in my master’s degree because of my own abilities.&nbsp;</p>
<section id="although-getting-a-degree-can-feel-like-an-endeavor-that-is-meant-to-be-shouldered-by-one-person-it-is-absolutely-not-designed-to-be-done-alone." class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="although-getting-a-degree-can-feel-like-an-endeavor-that-is-meant-to-be-shouldered-by-one-person-it-is-absolutely-not-designed-to-be-done-alone."><em>Although getting a degree can feel like an endeavor that is meant to be shouldered by one person, it is absolutely not designed to be done alone.</em></h4>
<p>My relationship with my master’s degree pivoted when I filled my “failures” with support from the people around me. There were two major steps I took: finding new mentors and changing my relationship with current ones.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="finding-new-mentors" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="finding-new-mentors"><strong>Finding New Mentors</strong></h3>
<p>Personally, I lacked confidence in discussing and presenting my research to other academics and knew that I needed help preparing for my oral defense. Because I knew my current mentors were extremely busy and could only offer me certan guidance, I attempted to expand my support. I employed the use of community or mosaic mentorship, which is the concept that mentorship should utilize the expertise of many mentors rather than a sole educator. I have written a blog on the impact of mosaic mentorship, which you can find below.&nbsp;</p>
<p>One of my professors gave our class the option to present our own research in class without the pressure of receiving a grade. I used it as an opportunity to receive feedback from my professor and my peers, as well as establish a mentor relationship with my professor. If you have similar fears as me, there are also “Grad Slams” on campus where graduate students present their work and receive useful critiques. It is a great opportunity to hear the frequently asked questions that might surface during your presentation.</p>
<p>When picking my committee members for my thesis, which are required for most master degrees, I emphasized early on that I needed support in professional development. My second committee member was able to meet with me once a month to help craft a larger picture of life outside of my master’s. During particularly difficult sections of my program, speaking with my second committee member helped motivate me and reminded me of why I was doing my master’s in the first place.&nbsp;</p>
<p><img src="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/mentormosaic2/Image_2.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="changing-relationships-with-past-mentors" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="changing-relationships-with-past-mentors"><strong>Changing relationships with past mentors:</strong></h3>
<p>While finding new mentors naturally made sense to me, it was difficult to realize that I was unable to maintain the same relationship with my previous mentors. Expectations of my work had changed, and with that, I needed to reestablish where I and my direct mentor stood.<br>
</p>
<section id="mentorship-involves-two-sides-of-a-professional-relationship.-as-your-mentor-recognizes-new-academic-potentials-within-you-you-must-be-able-to-reflect-the-same-onto-your-mentor." class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mentorship-involves-two-sides-of-a-professional-relationship.-as-your-mentor-recognizes-new-academic-potentials-within-you-you-must-be-able-to-reflect-the-same-onto-your-mentor."><em>Mentorship involves two sides of a professional relationship. As your mentor recognizes new academic potentials within you, you must be able to reflect the same onto your mentor.</em></h4>
<p>Although your mentor can have the best of intentions by entrusting more elaborate work onto you, it is important to understand boundaries and how to assert them. This can help your relationship with your mentor grow as well as maintain a good work-life balance.</p>
<p>What is a boundary? My therapist described a boundary as a statement and an action. A boundary is a statement that defines and protects your integrity. For example, I try to maintain work-life balance by minimizing how much I immediately reply to emails over the weekend. However, boundaries must be “I-centric”, as it defines what you will do if the other person disregards your statement. Thus a boundary is also an action.&nbsp;</p>
</section>
<section id="defining-your-boundaries-using-the-i-centric-model-is-both-empowering-and-realistic-as-you-are-not-telling-the-other-person-what-to-do-rather-what-you-will-do-if-that-boundary-is-crossed." class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="defining-your-boundaries-using-the-i-centric-model-is-both-empowering-and-realistic-as-you-are-not-telling-the-other-person-what-to-do-rather-what-you-will-do-if-that-boundary-is-crossed."><em>Defining your boundaries using the “I-centric” model is both empowering and realistic, as you are not telling the other person what to do, rather, what you will do if that boundary is crossed.</em>&nbsp;</h4>
<p>Continuing with my email example, rather than tell my mentor to not email over the weekend, I would inform them of my boundary: I won’t respond to emails over the weekend immediately, it’s best to contact me during the week. It’s to the point, polite, and defines your stance on a topic to your mentor.&nbsp;</p>
<p>I have found with mentors, students, friends, and family members alike, that undefined boundaries will be continually crossed over and over, many times without knowing the harm it is causing.&nbsp;</p>
<p>There may be circumstances where your boundaries will be tested, and in some cases, crossed. It is best to find a mentor who respects your boundaries and does not seek to alter your integrity regularly, whether or not they are doing this intentionally. If you find your mentor continually doing this, restating your boundaries is necessary.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Stating boundaries early in one’s mentorship will help your professional relationship, or in more extreme cases, signal to you that you may need to seek a different mentor.&nbsp;</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="in-summary" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="in-summary"><strong>In Summary:</strong></h3>
<p>Trusting another person with your academic and professional journey can be nerve wracking. Vulnerability gives others the ability to criticize you and your work, whether that criticism be hurtful or constructive.&nbsp;</p>
<p>However, creating a plan that fills your academic space with mentors who recognize your vulnerability and choose to uplift you will only enhance your professional journey.</p>
</section>
<section id="tdlr" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tdlr"><strong>TDLR:</strong></h3>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Recognizing that expectations placed on you by your mentor, program etc not only require changes within how you work to adapt, but also in your support system</p></li>
<li><p>You can adapt to handle more responsibilities, but your support and mentorship should equally increase. A mentorship plan will help you achieve this&nbsp;</p></li>
<li><p>A research proposal is different from a mentorship plan&nbsp;&nbsp;</p></li>
<li><p>An important aspect of a mentorship plan is receiving guidance from different people for different areas of your growth (Feel free to read my article “Mosaic Mentorship” for more on this)&nbsp;</p></li>
<li><p>As your academic goals develop, you may need new mentorship or current mentors to change their area of guidance&nbsp;</p></li>
<li><p>Vulnerability, at the face of supportive mentors, will help you grow tremendously&nbsp;</p></li>
</ol>


</section>
</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{kifer2022,
  author = {Kifer, Allison},
  title = {Incorporating a {Mentorship} {Plan} into {Your} {Degree}},
  date = {2022-10-26},
  url = {https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/mentormosaic2/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-kifer2022" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Kifer, Allison. 2022. <span>“Incorporating a Mentorship Plan into Your
Degree.”</span> October 26, 2022. <a href="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/mentormosaic2/">https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/mentormosaic2/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/mentormosaic2/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Why You Need Mosaic Mentorship</title>
  <dc:creator>Allison Kifer</dc:creator>
  <link>https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/mentormosaic/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Finding mentors and fostering relationships can be one of the most fulfilling and productive pursuits for undergraduates, graduate students, everyone.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/mentormosaic/priscilla-du-preez-unsplash.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Mentorship is a community effort.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="figuring-it-out-by-messing-it-all-up" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="figuring-it-out-by-messing-it-all-up">Figuring it out by messing it all up</h2>
<p>In my third year at UCSD, I was thrilled to have found a professor who 1) embodied my interest in merging science and writing and 2) had genuine enthusiasm in my professional development. With the right program, he encouraged me that he would be able to support my independent research ventures. The TRELS program at UCSD was the perfect platform for me to both explore the communication of climate change and completely botch my mentorship with a professor.</p>
<p>Although this was not my intention, the experience taught me an important lesson that I wished I understood earlier during my time at UCSD.</p>
<p>How exactly did I achieve this? The Triton Research &amp; Experiential Learning Scholars (TRELS) program was the first platform I had been granted to express and develop my academic interests with a professor. I immediately poured all parts of myself into this project and, in doing so, asked too much of my mentor.</p>
<p>I wanted to explore human language, to understand how the structure of words in a sentence could have an impact on how we perceive and make decisions about climate change. I wished to investigate decades of discussions surrounding global warming and how this history perpetuates misinformation we still see today. I sought to labor through dense climate reports and reference the well researched biology, chemistry, and physics that already existed.</p>
<p>And beyond my research paper, I had an innate desire to understand who exactly I was becoming in my journey of personal and professional development. While I rejected it at the time, my identity was intricately woven between my interests.</p>
<p>It was only after I told this story to another professor of mine did the reality of my “plan” of mentorship come crashing down. No one person would be able to appeal to all the facets of my interests and needs in my academic development. I needed a linguist, a historian, and a climate scientist at least to aid me in my research goals , and instead, I had brought these expectations into my mentorship with a single professor.</p>
<p><img src="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/mentormosaic/dylan-ferreira-unsplash.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>I’ll admit I’m being a little hard on my third-year self, as the pursuit for mentorship is self-motivated on a large public campus such as UCSD.</p>
<p>University is many students’ first opportunity to dictate their education. Many students are coming from high school where education is driven by obligation, and most classes, teachers, and times of instruction are assigned with little student input. Upon entering UCSD, I found myself in control of my chosen degree with the exception of a few administrative nudges in the right direction in order to graduate on time. The void of academic constraint was suddenly overflowing with choices I had to make, and after planning out the first few quarters at UCSD, I was satiated with my own involvement in my undergraduate degree. Directing my own mentorship, which would include the close involvement of PhD-holding professors, was completely absent from my mind.</p>
<section id="however-as-i-became-more-comfortable-with-the-campus-i-realized-that-there-was-an-unavoidably-large-piece-of-my-education-missing---mentorship." class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="however-as-i-became-more-comfortable-with-the-campus-i-realized-that-there-was-an-unavoidably-large-piece-of-my-education-missing---mentorship."><em>However, as I became more comfortable with the campus, I realized that there was an unavoidably large piece of my education missing - mentorship.</em></h4>
<p>By my third year, when I had finally found a professor who acknowledged my interests as something worth investing in, I didn’t know how to ask for what I needed. After months of searching for a professor to represent me and my academic growth, I came into my mentorship starstruck and unable to use critical thinking. I was looking for too much guidance in too many places, all the while not really knowing what I was looking for.</p>
<p>Luckily, upon reflection, this problem has a dynamic solution.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="mosaic-mentorship" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mosaic-mentorship">Mosaic mentorship</h2>
<p>What I needed in the past was a community of mentors full of niche, yet separate, roles in my progression of research and sense of self as an academic. While relatively new, the concept of community or “mosaic” mentorship, or the incorporation of an array of diverse mentors into a student’s professional growth, has been thought to better aid mentees (Khatchikian, Chahal, and Kielar, 2021).</p>
<p>I was able to experience the benefits of mosaic mentorship firsthand, as I incorporated a community of mentors into my master’s program. A master’s in biology at UCSD includes performing two years of lab research under the guidance of a Principal Investigator (PI) and synthesizing your findings into a written and oral thesis. In addition to your PI, you need at least two more UCSD professionals or thesis committee members in order to complete your master’s. While my PI aided me in my direct research, my committee members gave me a wide perspective of the field and how to effectively communicate science.</p>
<p>Additionally, having two, three, four perspectives on a collection of topics allowed me to critically think about my lab PI’s advice and guidance.</p>
<section id="while-a-professors-opinion-may-be-trying-to-steer-you-in-the-right-direction-for-their-profession-this-may-not-actually-be-where-you-are-wanting-to-take-your-development.-rather-than-become-a-parrot-of-your-mentors-advice-with-mosaic-mentorship-you-are-able-to-synthesize-collective-thought-to-become-the-researcher-you-are-aiming-to-be." class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="while-a-professors-opinion-may-be-trying-to-steer-you-in-the-right-direction-for-their-profession-this-may-not-actually-be-where-you-are-wanting-to-take-your-development.-rather-than-become-a-parrot-of-your-mentors-advice-with-mosaic-mentorship-you-are-able-to-synthesize-collective-thought-to-become-the-researcher-you-are-aiming-to-be."><em>While a professor’s opinion may be trying to steer you in the right direction for their profession, this may not actually be where you are wanting to take your development. Rather than become a parrot of your mentor’s advice, with mosaic mentorship you are able to synthesize collective thought to become the researcher you are aiming to be.</em></h4>
<p>Mosaic mentorship also benefits your mentor too. All professors at UCSD do work outside of the classroom and most likely cannot offer you the complete mentorship you are looking for, even if they are enthusiastic about working with you. Mosaic mentorship respects the time of your mentors by dividing up the amount of mentorship you need to succeed.</p>
<p>Mentorship completely enlivened my experience at UCSD. Learning facts about biology was what I came to UCSD to do, but becoming scientifically literate and fostering my own sense of professional identity was the most important part of the process. And this is not only true for me– it has been shown that students mentored in academia tended to self-identify as a scientist more than those without a mentor (Atkins <em>et al.</em>, 2020). It is difficult to feel a part of the academic community without a group of people there to champion and advocate for you.</p>
<p>University is a place to find inspiration for your academic goals, but it is ultimately up to you to invest in your interests. I was never taught how to effectively pursue mentorship, and it took a few mistakes to finalize what I needed. You will most likely continue to make mistakes along your mentorship journey, but I can assure you that it will be worth it.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="tldr" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tldr">TLDR</h2>
<p>If you want the short version of this article:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Mentorship is as useful, if not more, than the education you receive in class</p></li>
<li><p>Prioritize your mentorship plan in university. Locate multiple mentors and ask for different support from each</p></li>
<li><p>Consistently reach out to new mentors or check in with your established mentors a few times a quarter</p></li>
</ul>
<p>What do you look for in a mentor and how do you find one? That’s a whole article in itself. Here are a few quick places for UCSD folks looking mentorship:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Mentoring for All Initiative</p></li>
<li><p>Take some time to look through the UCSD Faculty List to find researchers who interest you</p></li>
<li><p>Consider going to the many presentations by academics on campus or online</p></li>
<li><p>Reach out to Assistant Professors, Post-Doctorates, Adjunct Professors at the Salk Institute, TAs and more. Mentorship can and should come from all places</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Continue the conversation, feel free to reach out to me.</p>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="references">References</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00261-021-03314-2" class="uri">https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00261-021-03314-2</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://stemeducationjournal.springeropen.com/articles/10.1186/s40594-020-00242-3" class="uri">https://stemeducationjournal.springeropen.com/articles/10.1186/s40594-020-00242-3</a></p></li>
</ul>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{kifer2022,
  author = {Kifer, Allison},
  title = {Why {You} {Need} {Mosaic} {Mentorship}},
  date = {2022-10-08},
  url = {https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/mentormosaic/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-kifer2022" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Kifer, Allison. 2022. <span>“Why You Need Mosaic Mentorship.”</span>
October 8, 2022. <a href="https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/mentormosaic/">https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/mentormosaic/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://reutherlab.netlify.app/docs/blog/posts/mentormosaic/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
